Finding Aid for Women's Athletics (University of Michigan) records, 1972-1990
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Women's Athletics (University of Michigan) records 1972-1990
University of Michigan. Women's Athletics.
9 linear feet
91438 Bimu F84 2
Administrative unit of the University of Michigan Athletic Department responsible for management of women's varsity sports. Records, including topical files, committee minutes, administrative files, and materials on Title IX, document the period when Womens Athletics operated as a semi-autonomous unit under a Director of Women's Athletics.
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The records (Accession No. 7902 ) were transferred in two accessions: two feet from Phyllis Ocker, Associate Director of Women's Athletics, in December 1990 and six feet from the Women's Athletics office in August 1992 through Sandi Burdi
The collection is open to research except for the folder "Athletic Scholarship Information" in box 8.
By provenance, the Women's Athletics records are properly a subgroup of the University of Michigan Department of Intercollegiate Athletics record group. To enhance access, these records of the Women's Athletics office have been broken out and described separately. Additional material on women's athletics, including media guides, game programs, press releases, and news clippings can be found in the Sports Information Department subgroup of the University of Michigan Department of Intercollegiate Athletics records.
Prior to 1969, women's sports at the University of Michigan were organized under the Women's Athletic Association (WAA), a student-run organization which was affiliated with the Athletic Conference of American College Women. (For historical background on the WAA, see The University of Michigan An Encyclopedic Survey, Volume IV, available at the Bentley Historical Library.) With the merger of the men's and women's physical education departments in 1970, the WAA was disbanded and individual sports for women were managed and financially supported by student clubs.
The turning point in the development of women's intercollegiate sports at the university came in 1972, when the United States Congress passed Title IX of the Education Amendment Act. Title IX banned sexual discrimination in education programs which received federal funding. In the realm of athletics, it required universities which received federal funding to provide equal athletic opportunities for men and women.
In the early 1970s, women athletes at Michigan had complained that the university distributed scholarships unfairly, provided women with less coaching time than men, allocated less travel money to women, and denied equal opportunities for the recruitment of women athletes. Forced to respond to both Title IX and the complaints, President Robben Fleming established the Committee to Study Intercollegiate Athletics for Women (commonly referred to as the "Burns Committee") in 1973 to investigate the development of women's intercollegiate (varsity) sports. Upon the recommendations of the Burns Committee's preliminary report in August 1973 and final report in November 1973, the university established six varsity sports for women in the 1973/74 school year: tennis, basketball, swimming and diving, synchronized swimming, volleyball, and field hockey.
The new women's athletic program was placed under the administrative control of the Department of Intercollegiate Athletics and the Board in Control of Intercollegiate Athletics. It was headed by an Associate Director of Women's Intercollegiate Athletics reporting to the Athletic Director. Marie Hartwig was named the first women's athletic director. An Advisory Committee on Women's Intercollegiate Athletics was appointed to assist her in developing and operating the women's varsity program. This committee was also to serve as a search committee for the next associate director. Hartwig retired in 1976 and was succeeded as associate director by Virginia Hunt, who held the position for less than one year. In 1977 Phyllis Ocker was named associate director of women's athletics. Ocker had been a staff member of the university since 1961, serving as assistant professor in the School of Education, and as field hockey coach (1974-1978). Ocker was succeeded by Peggy Bradley-Doppes in 1991.
From 1974 to 1981, women's sports at Michigan operated according to the rules of the Association of Intercollegiate Athletics for Women, a national organization that tried to provide women's athletics with an alternative to the NCAA. Michigan's women's teams competed in two intercollegiate associations: the Midwest Association of Intercollegiate Athletics for Women (MAIAW) and the State of Michigan Association of Intercollegiate Athletics for Women (SMAIAW).
In 1981 women's varsity sports at the university came under the aegis of the NCAA, and began competing in the Big Ten conference. This was a controversial move as many women believed it decreased the amount of input women had in the administration and development of their varsity sports and represented a very different philosophy of women's sports than that of the AIAW.
The university's compliance with Title IX was slow, leading to the filing of additional complaints and to investigations by the Department of Health Education and Welfare in the late 1970s. These, in turn, led to an expansion of the women's program and an increase in financial support for women athletes, although it was not until 1989 that the university fully complied with Title IX in the area of scholarships.
Phyllis Ocker retired in December 1990. She led the struggle for women's athletics at the university during difficult and trying years. By the time she stepped down, the number of varsity sports for women had grown to eleven, (gymnastics, softball, cross country, soccer, track, and golf were added, synchronized swimming was dropped) and total spending for women's athletics had increased from $100,000 to $2.4 million.
The Women's Athletics records are arranged in five series:
Administrative Records, 1971-1989, (2.0 linear ft.) including a Topical File, 1973-1989, minutes of committees and the Board in Control of Athletics, correspondence, budget material, and yearly files on individual sports
Conferences and Governing Bodies, 1973-1989, (4.5 linear ft.) consisting of minutes, reports, and correspondence of committees and governing bodies including the AIAW, MAIAW, SMAIAW, and Big Ten
Title IX material, 1973-1988 (2.3 linear ft.
Phyllis Ocker Personal Material (0.2 Linear ft.)
Photographs (0.1 linear ft.)
Within individual folders the records are often arranged in reverse chronological order.
The Women's Athletics records document the evolution of varsity sports for women at the University of Michigan, and the struggles women engaged in for equity in funding, coaching, facilities, and scholarships. The bulk of the collection represents the administrative files from Phyllis Ocker's tenure as Associate Director for Women's Intercollegiate Athletics. The records document the internal development and management of the women's athletics program, governance of women's athletics through the various intercollegiate conferences and associations with which the program was affiliated, the implementation of Title IX and subsequent internal and external complaints and investigations, and the management and operation of individual sports teams. (Additional material, including media guides, game programs, and photographs for individual sports teams, and microfilmed news clipping scrapbooks can be found in the Bentley Library in the records of the University of Michigan, Department of Intercollegiate Athletics, Sports Information Office.)
Subject
Hartwig, Marie Dorothy.; Ocker, Phyllis.; Midwest Association of Intercollegiate Athletics for Women.; State of Michigan Association of Intercollegiate Athletics for Women.; University of Michigan--Sports.; University of Michigan. Board in Control of Intercollegiate Athletics.; University of Michigan. Athletic Dept.; University of Michigan--Students.; University of Michigan. Women's Athletics.; Sex discrimination in sports--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Sports for women--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Women college students--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
- Administrative Records 1971-1988
  The Administrative Records series documents the work of a number of departmental and university committees and the management of the women's athletics program. The principal files in the Administrative Records series include: Topical File, Advisory Committee on Recreation, Intramurals, and Sports Clubs; Advisory Committee on Women's Intercollegiate Athletics; Board in Control of Intercollegiate Athletics; Budget; Salary and Personnel; Championships and Tournaments Hosted; and Individual Sports.
  - Topical File
    The Topical File, arranged alphabetically, includes information on a variety of administrative and policy issues. Among the significant files are the "Burns Committee Report," 1973, advocating the establishment of a full program of intercollegiate sports for women and exploring the requirements for facilities, coaching, organizational framework, and finances; the "M Award Controversy" includes correspondence on the debate over whether women varsity athletes should receive the same "M" letter award as male athletes, with correspondents including Don Canham, "Bo" Schembechler, Johnny Orr, members of the "M Club" and several women alumni; "Admissions Information" includes material on procedures and guidelines for recruiting women athletes; and the "Academic Advisory Committee," 1977-1985 file containing minutes, reports and statistics on academic eligibility and performance by sport. The file on "Athletic Scholarship Information" is closed to researchers for FERPA privacy reasons. It includes yearly information on the number and amount of athletic scholarships and other financial aid awarded to women athletes.
    - Academic Performance Committee 1977-1985 (Box 1)
      (includes minutes and team statistics re: academic eligibility of athletes)
    - Admissions Information 1975-1981 (Box 1)
      (includes procedures and guidelines for recruiting female athletes)
    - American Council on Education (ACE) Committee on Collegiate Athletics 1977-1978 (Box 1)
    - Athletic Scholarship Information 1976/77-1983/84 (Box 8)
      (includes lists of awards granted and correspondence)
      [CLOSED]
    - Awards and Scholarships 1974-1988 (Box 1)
    - Basketball Marketing and Promotion 1983-1988 (Box 1)
    - Basketball, NCAA Tournament 1990 (Box 1)
    - Black Athlete Panel 1981 (Box 1)
      (notes for MLK Day presentation)
    - Burns Committee Report 1973 (Box 1)
    - Cheerleaders, Regulations and Selection 1986-1987 (Box 1)
    - "Ethics and the Amateur Principle in Women's Sports," Conference 1975 (Box 1)
      (mostly administrative)
    - Field Hockey Camp 1980 (Box 1)
    - Fundraising 1979-1982 (Box 1)
    - Golf Fundraiser (Box 1)
    - 1986 (Box 1)
    - 1987 (Box 1)
    - 1988 (Box 1)
      (includes photos)
    - "M-Women" Award 1982-1983 (Box 1)
    - Marie Hartwig Award 1982-1988 (Box 1)
    - Mentor Program 1985 (Box 1)
    - Physical Education Referent Group (Michigan Dept. of Education) circa 1976 (Box 1)
    - Procedures Manual 1977 (Box 1)
    - Synchronized Swimming, List Letter Winners and Misc. Correspondence 1974-1982 (Box 1)
    - Tenth Anniversary Celebration 1983 (Box 1)
    - Varsity Arena (Matt Mann Pool Conversion) 1988-1989, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Advisory Committee on Women's Intercollegiate Athletics 1975-1976
    The Advisory Committee on Women's Intercollegiate Athletics, 1974-1976, was formed to assist the Director of Women's Athletics in developing and operating the women's varsity program. It also acted as a search committee to replace Women's Athletic Director Marie Hartwig in 1976. The file includes minutes, correspondence, and reports as well as petitions to establish new sports at the varsity level. The folder for 1974 includes a brief summary of the committee's work.
    - 1974 (Box 1)
      (includes a summary of committees' work)
    - 1975 (Box 1)
    - 1976 (Box 1)
    - Petitions for varsity status 1973-1977 (Box 1)
  - Board In Control of Intercollegiate Athletics
    The Board in Control of Intercollegiate Athletics file (boxes 2 and 8) contains minutes and some correspondence of three committees of the Board as well as minutes and correspondence of the Board itself, 1976-May 1988. The Long Range Planning Committee, 1976-1979, dealt primarily with the establishment of new varsity sports for women but considered many aspects many aspects of Title IX implementation. The Women's Athletics Committee, 1976-1980, is a small file of minutes and notes relating primarily to the governance and administration of women's athletics. The Board in Control minutes file appears to be a complete run of minutes from the time Phyllis Ocker became Associate Athletic Director through May 1988. This complements the Board in Control minutes found in the Don Canham papers and the Board in Control of Intercollegiate Athletics records.
    - Long Range Planning Committee 1976-1979 (Box 2)
      (includes memos and minutes, mostly regarding creation of new varsity sports)
    - Faculty Rep. Selection Committee 1980 (Box 2)
    - Women's Athletics Committee 1976-1980 (Box 2)
    - Minutes (correspondence and other material)
      - 1976/77 (also includes copies of some minutes of Advisory Committee on Women's Athletics) (Box 8)
      - September 17, 1977-June 1979 (Box 8)
      - July 1979-June 1981 (Box 8)
      - Sept 1981-June 1983 (Box 8)
      - September 1983-April 1985 (Box 8)
      - May 1985-May 1986 (Box 8)
      - May 1986-Jan 1987 (Box 8)
      - February-April 1987 (Box 8)
      - May-December 1987 (Box 8)
      - January-June 1988 (Box 8)
  - Budget Materials
    The Budget and Salary Personnel files contain summary reports on yearly expenditures and income by sport and on coaches salaries as well as some correspondence relating to hiring of coaches.
    - Budget Summaries
      - 1974/75-1975/76 (Box 2)
      - 1976/77-1985/86 (by sport), 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Club Sports
    - Records 1971-1973 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence
    - Academic Affairs, Vice President 1973/74 (Box 2)
      (regarding financing women's sports)
    - Miscellaneous 1972-1988 (Box 2)
    - Coaches 1973-1981 (Box 2)
    - Scholarships and Admissions 1973-1977 (Box 2)
      (a selection of letters)
    - Departmental
      - 1973-1979 (Box 2)
      - 1980-1985 (Box 2)
  - Salary and Personnel
    (corresp. on hiring of coaches and salaries)
    - 1974-1978 (Box 2)
    - 1979 (Box 2)
    - 1980-1984 (Box 2)
  - Championships and Tournaments Hosted 1978-1989
    Championships and Tournaments Hosted includes administrative and publicity material for AIAW, Big Ten, MAIAW, and SMAIAW championships held at Michigan as well the Dominos Wolverine Classic basketball tournament and the Nike Classic field hockey tournament. Some files contain tournament programs and official results.
    - AIAW, Synchronized Swimming National 1980 (Box 2)
    - Big Ten
      - Golf 1986 (Box 2)
      - Gymnastics 1982 (Box 2)
      - Softball 1982 (Box 2)
      - Swimming and Diving 1989 (Box 2)
      - Track, Indoor 1987, 3 folders (Box 2)
      - Track, Outdoor 1988 (Women & Men) (Box 2)
    - MAIAW
      - Softball 1982 (Box 2)
      - Synchronized Swimming 1978, 1979 (Box 2)
      - Swimming 1978 (Box 2)
    - SMAIAW
      - Softball 1981 (Box 2)
      - Tennis 1977, 1978 (Box 2)
    - Dominos Classic (basketball)
      - 1981-1983 (Box 2)
      - 1984 (Box 2)
    - Nike Classic (field hockey) 1982 (Box 2)
  - Individual Sports 1972-1987
    The Individual Sports, 1972-1988 file is comprised of correspondence, budget information, rosters, clippings, and occasional season summaries prepared by coaches which assess overall performances of individual teams. The file is arranged by year and sport.
    - 1972/73
      - Competitive swimming (Box 3)
      - Tennis (Box 3)
    - 1973/74
      - Basketball
        - General (Box 3)
        - Budget (Box 3)
      - Budget (Box 3)
      - Field Hockey
        - General (Box 3)
        - Budget (Box 3)
      - Injuries (accident reports) (Box 3)
      - Medical exams (Box 3)
      - Officiating (Box 3)
      - Skiing (Box 3)
        (petition for recognition as intercollegiate sport)
      - Competitive Swimming And Diving
        - General (Box 3)
        - Budget (Box 3)
      - Synchronized swimming
        - General (Box 3)
        - Budget (Box 3)
      - Tennis
        - General (Box 3)
        - Budget (Box 3)
      - Volleyball
        - General (Box 3)
          (season summary prepared by team manager)
        - Budget (Box 3)
    - 1974/75
      - Athletes (master list by sport) (Box 3)
      - Basketball (season summary) (Box 3)
      - Budget (Box 3)
      - Field Hockey (season summary) (Box 3)
      - Gymnastics (petition for intercollegiate status) (Box 3)
      - Injuries (includes miscellaneous accident reports) (Box 3)
      - Swimming and Diving (season summary prepared by coach) (Box 3)
      - Synchronized Swimming (season summary prepared by coach) (Box 3)
      - Tennis (Box 3)
      - Volleyball (Box 3)
    - 1975/76
      - Women's Varsity Sports 1975/76 (Box 3)
        (Prospects for 1975/76 and 1974/75 season review)
      - Basketball (Box 3)
      - Field Hockey (season summary) (Box 3)
      - Injuries (Box 3)
      - Insurance Coverage (Box 3)
      - Gymnastics (Box 3)
      - Swimming (Box 3)
      - Synchronized Swimming (Box 3)
        (Includes neg. of 1976 team photo)
      - Tennis (Box 3)
      - Track (Box 3)
      - Volleyball (Box 3)
    - 1977-1987
      - Basketball 1977-1979 (Box 3)
      - Cross Country 1987 (Box 3)
      - Field Hockey 1977, 1981 newsletter (Box 3)
      - Soccer 1987 (Box 3)
      - Softball 1986 (Box 3)
      - Swimming 1982/83 (Box 3)
      - Synchronized Swimming 1977-1984
        - General (Box 3)
        - Dissolution As Varsity Sport 1982 (Box 3)
- Conferences and Governing Bodies 1972-1989
  The Conferences and Governing Bodies series includes several of the most important files documenting Women's Athletics participation in three intercollegiate athletic associations: the MAIAW (Midwest Association of Intercollegiate Athletics for Women), the SMAIAW (State of Michigan Association of Intercollegiate Athletics for Women), and the Big Ten. All of these files contain information on the governance of women's athletics programs at Michigan and other schools, the conduct of sports sponsored by the associations, the histories of the associations, and to some extent the "philosophy" of women's athletics.
  - CCWAA (Council of Collegiate Women's Athletic Administrators) 1983-1989
    - Newsletter
      - 1983-1985 (Box 3)
      - 1986-1989 (Box 3)
  - MAIAW (Midwest Association of Intercollegiate Athletics for Women) 1972-1983
    The MAIAW series, 1972-1983, includes a historical review of the association, handbooks outlining regulations and procedures, and minutes of the commissioners' meetings.
    - Historical Review (1983 ?) (Box 3)
    - Handbook
      - 1973-1980 (Box 3)
      - 1981 (Box 3)
    - Minutes
      - 1972-1975 (Box 3)
      - 1976-1977 (Box 3)
      - 1978-1979 (Box 3)
      - 1980-1983 (Box 3)
    - Policies and Procedures 1975-1981 (Box 3)
  - SMAIAW (State of Michigan Association of Intercollegiate Athletics for Women) 1972-1981
    The SMAIAW file includes the constitution and bylaws of the association, handbooks, commissioners' minutes, and policies and procedures for each sponsored sport.
    - Constitution and Bylaws (Box 4)
    - Handbooks 1969-1978, 3 volumes (Box 4)
    - Minutes
      - 1972/73-1973/74 (Box 4)
      - 1974/75 (Box 4)
      - 1975/76 (Box 4)
      - 1976/77 (Box 4)
      - 1977/78 (Box 4)
      - 1979/80-1080/81 (Box 4)
    - Policies and Procedures (by sport) (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous 1973-1975 (Box 4)
  - AIAW (Association for Intercollegiate Athletics for Women)
    - Correspondence
      - 1973-1974 (Box 9)
      - 1975 (Box 9)
      - 1976-1977 (Box 9)
      - 1978- 1979-1980 (Box 9)
      - 1981-1982 (Box 9)
    - Minutes of National Meetings
      - 1974 (Box 9)
      - 1975 (Box 9)
      - 1976 (Box 9)
      - 1977, 2 folders (Box 9)
      - 1978, 2 folders (Box 9)
      - 1979, 2 folders (Box 9)
      - 1980 (Box 9)
      - 1981, 2 folders (Box 9)
      - 1982 (Box 9)
  - Big Ten 1982-1989
    - Advisory Commission, Minutes 1986-1987 (Box 4)
    - Athletic Directors Minutes
      - April 22-December 2 1986 (Box 4)
      - January 1987-May 3, 1988 (Box 4)
    - Conference Governance Retreat 1987-1988 (Box 4)
    - Extra Events Committee (Women's Sports Festival)
      - 1982-1983, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - 1984 (Box 4)
    - Field Hockey
      - Game Management Guide 1986-1989 (Box 4)
      - New Conference 1980 (Box 4)
    - Faculty Representatives Minutes
      - 1982-1983 (Box 4)
      - 1984 (Box 4)
      - 1985-1986 (Box 4)
      - 1987 (Box 4)
    - Governance of Women's Athletics 1976-1980 (Box 4)
    - Joint Group
      - Chronology with minutes of first meetings 1976 (Box 5)
      - Minutes
        - 1982-1983 (Box 5)
        - 1984 (Box 5)
        - 1985 (Box 5)
        - 1986 (Box 5)
        - 1987 (Box 5)
        - 1988 (Box 5)
    - "Lost Class Time Surveys," 1982-1985 (Box 5)
    - Penn State Integration (Box 5)
    - Women's Sports Committees, Minutes etc
      - Basketball 1981-1987 (Box 5)
      - Golf 1983-1985 (Box 5)
      - Gymnastics 1982-1987 (Box 5)
      - Tennis 1985-1987 (Box 5)
      - Track 1982-1986 (Box 5)
      - Volleyball
        - 1982-1984 (Box 5)
        - 1985-1987 (Box 5)
    - Women's Officiating Committee Minutes
      - 1983-1984 (Box 5)
      - 1985-1988 (Box 5)
    - Women's Program Group
      - Minutes
        - September-December, 1981 (Box 5)
        - 1982 (Box 5)
        - January-May 1983 (Box 5)
        - September-December,1983 (Box 5)
        - 1984 (Box 5)
        - January-May 1985 (Box 5)
    - Women's Athletics Administrators
      - Minutes
        (continues minutes of Women's Program Group)
        - May-December 1985 (Box 6)
        - January-April, 1986 (Box 6)
        - May-December 1986 (Box 6)
        - 1987 (Box 6)
        - 1988 (Box 6)
- Title IX 1972-1986
  The implementation of Title IX regulations concerning women's athletics at Michigan (and to some extent at other schools) is documented in the Title IX subgroup. The file "Chronology of Implementation" provides a brief introduction to the university's and the Athletic Department's response to Title IX and the development of women's varsity sports through 1979. The "Correspondence and Reports" file was compiled by the women's athletics administrators. It includes correspondence of the administrators as well as copies of Title IX related correspondence between other university officials such as Don Canham, Virginia Nordby, President Robben Fleming, university legal counsel, and the Board in Control; officials of the MAIAW, Big Ten conference and other Big Ten schools; and the Department of Health Education and Welfare. This is probably the most complete single file of Title IX correspondence, but the researcher should also examine other collections including Donald Canham, Eunice Burns, Marie Hartwig, and Marcus Plant and other members of the Board in Control of Athletics, as well as the records of various U of M administrative offices including the President, General Counsel, Vice-President for Academic Affairs, Office of Student Affairs, and Affirmative Action Office.